Richard Wise

Lead Software Engineer

Richard Wise

583 Shady Hollow New Braunfels, TX 78132

830-515-6455 rwwise@gmail.com

—

Skills

Java, CI/CD, Terraform, AWS, SQL, GIT, Gradle **Objective**: I am a Lead Software Engineer with over 25-years of deep technical experience across multiple domains, technologies and disciplines. I am seeking a Staff Engineer or Staff Technical Architect role that allows me to continue designing, building and implementing technical solutions to solve complex business problems. I am passionate about learning & development, mentoring junior developers and AWS cloud technologies.

Experience

USAA / Lead Software Engineer

2017 - 2023, San Antonio, TX

Serves as team lead over a group of highly motivated, engaged and passionate engineer subject-matter experts, responsible for the technical onboarding and professional development of USAA's new and experienced software / data engineer hires. Provides oversight and alignment to USAA architecture of multiple technology programs supporting JAVA/API, Data & Analytics, Front-End, as well as more advanced programs in AWS Cloud and Spring Boot. Responsible for working closely with junior developers, technical SMEs, management and USAA technical thought leaders to build sustainable and scalable learning solutions for the technology community.

Represents the Chief Technology Office (CTO) as architect delegate and an active voice for the IT's Learning and Development organization. Responsible for understanding USAA's technology roadmap and collaborating with CTO's architecture and portfolio owner community to ensure the alignment of our learning needs to the strategic modernization efforts of the business. Additionally responsible for ensuring the organization's applications and accesses adhere to all required architectural reviews, security evaluations, and meet all CTO documentation standards.

As part of USAA's cloud modernization journey lead multiple one-week technical training for experienced USAA engineers on building AWS cloud applications, with a heavy focus on Terraform, EKS and Lambda.

USAA / Senior Software Engineer

2014 - 2017, San Antonio, TX

Developed and executed an IT Onboarding program that reduced time to effectiveness from 18 months to 10 weeks. This program focused on hands-on application development, Testing, CI/CD, and Agile knowledge. Built a team of multidiscipline software and data engineers applying this program across all of USAA IT disciplines.

USAA / Senior Software Engineer

2012 - 2014, San Antonio, TX

Java Domain Lead worked to improve and support all development tools used for Java

coding at USAA.

USAA / Senior Software Engineer

2009 - 2012, San Antonio, TX

Production Support for USAA Application Infrastructure team and implementation of a Reference Data Solution for enterprise use.

USAA / Senior Software Engineer

2007 - 2009, San Antonio, TX

Implemented multiple changes and provided production support to USAA Security Infrastructure.

CTRC / Senior Portal Engineer

2005 - 2007, San Antonio, TX

Architected, built and rolled out Prod, Test, Dev hardware and software environments, from Racking the Servers, Change Management, Business Requirements, Development, and Production support of a Web Portal Environment.

Hibernia National Bank, Inc. / Application Program Analyst II

2002 - 2005, New Orleans, LA

Responsible for gathering, analyzing, and organizing customer requests for changes to CRM applications into projects, and then developing, testing and deploying these projects.

Certia, Inc. / Senior Java Client/Server Developer

2000 - 2002, New Orleans, LA

Built and Maintained custom application server for Secure Mail application. Contributed to a Patent on DRM solution for Secure Mail.

Venture Transport, Inc. / Client/Server Developer and Webmaster

1998 - 2000, New Orleans, LA

Built and maintained website and provided support for in-house developed logistics system.

Education

Nicholls State University / B.Sc. Computer Science

1998, Thibodaux Louisiana